Sunday, April 29, 1945, one week before the end of World War II in Europe.
The 45th Infantry Division of the US Seventh Army liberates Dachau,
the first regular concentration camp built by the Nazi government.
American soldiers smell not only human excrement, but also decomposing bodies,
which causes many of them to cry or vomit. In addition,
They found more than 30 railway cars full of corpses and 30 thousand survivors.
in a state of extreme emaciation, so much so that they looked like walking skeletons.
The vast majority of them were seriously ill. Many will die.
from typhus and starvation during the months following the liberation of the camp.
The shocked and furious American military, as well as the prisoners who
They survived years of humiliation and abuse at the hands of their Nazi tormentors, and they want revenge.
and his brutal response is yet to come. After Adolf Hitler was appointed
Chancellor of Germany on January 30, 1933, the National Socialists used a series of
measures of terror to gradually establish a dictatorship throughout the country.
The main objective of the first concentration camps of the 1930s was to imprison
and intimidate the leaders of the political, social and cultural movements that the Nazis
considered a threat to the survival and expansion of the regime. In these fields,
The prisoners lived in fear of the terrible violence exercised by the SS.
The first concentration camp created by the Nazis was Dachau, located near Munich,
in March 1933. On March 22, this place received its first prisoners.
In October of that same year, Dachau commandant Theodor Eicke introduced a system
of horrible punishments for prisoners who committed minor offenses. In this way,
Eicke made sure that Dachau served as a model for all concentration camps.
futures. It also became a training center or "school of violence"
"for the SS guards who would later work in other concentration camps.
During the first year, Dachau had the capacity to house 5,000 prisoners. At first,
The inmates were mainly German communists, social democrats,
trade unionists and other political opponents of the Nazi regime. However, over time,
Jehovah's Witnesses, Roma, Sinti, homosexuals, were also interned at Dachau.
repeat offenders and the so-called "antisocial" people, that is, those
that the regime imprisoned because they could not or would not find paid employment.
During the first years, relatively few Jews were interned in this camp.
of concentration. The Hebrews who were sent to this place belonged to some
of the groups mentioned or had violated the Nuremberg Laws of 1935. These codes
addressed the racial issue in Nazi ideology. In early 1937, the SS, with the help of manpower
of prisoners, began construction of a large complex on the grounds of the original camp,
destroying the old ammunition factory, which was in terrible condition.
This work was officially completed in mid-August 1938, remaining, without further changes,
until the end of the war in 1945. The number of Jewish prisoners at Dachau increased
due to the increase in their persecution. On November 10 and 11, 1938,
After Kristallnacht, when the Nazi SA, along with the German civilian population,
They looted homes, businesses, synagogues, hospitals and Jewish schools, and sent
nearly 11,000 Jews to the Dachau concentration camp. Most of these people were
released after being imprisoned for a few weeks to a few months, after demonstrating that many
of them intended to emigrate from Germany. Dahua was divided into two sections:
the camp area and the crematorium area. The camp area consisted of 32 barracks,
including one for priests imprisoned for opposing the regime
Nazi and another reserved for medical experiments. The camp administration was located in the
main entrance. This sector had buildings with kitchen, laundry, showers and workshops. Without
However, the most important structure was the bunker. Detention in the bunker was a method
which allowed the SS to isolate rebellious and defiant prisoners from other inmates.
They were subjected to long confinements, torture and, finally, death.
The courtyard between the prison and the central kitchen was used
for the systematic execution of prisoners. An electrified barbed wire fence,
A ditch and a wall with seven watchtowers surrounded the field.
Following the outbreak of World War II on September 1, 1939,
The living conditions of the prisoners at the Dachau concentration camp worsened
drastically. The poor working conditions, the shortage of rations and the lack of hygiene
caused an increase in mortality. From 1940 onwards, more and more inmates
were transported to the Dachau concentration camp from the
countries occupied by the German armed forces. The crematorium area was built next to the camp
main in 1942. This new crematorium included a gas chamber. However,
There is no conclusive evidence that this gas chamber was used to murder human beings.
Instead, prisoners were subjected to so-called "selection." All those who were
considered too sick or weak to continue working, were sent to the center
Extermination by "euthanasia" at Hartheim, near Linz, Austria. More than 2,500 prisoners
from Dachau were murdered in the gas chambers of Hartheim. Likewise,
mass executions by firing squad, first in the courtyard of the bunker and later in a field
specially designed shooting range by the SS. Thousands of prisoners were murdered there, including
at least 4,000 Soviet prisoners of war after the invasion of the Soviet Union in 1941.
Beginning in 1942, German doctors began conducting clinical experiments on prisoners of war.
Dachau. Doctors and scientists from the Luftwaffe (the German Air Force) and the Experimental Institute
German Aviation carried out high altitude and hypothermia tests, as well as tests for
to test methods for purifying seawater. These efforts were aimed at
assist German pilots carrying out bombing raids or who were shot down in icy waters.
German scientists also conducted experiments to test the effectiveness of products
pharmaceuticals against diseases such as malaria and tuberculosis. Hundreds of prisoners died
or were permanently disabled as a result of these experiments.
The prisoners at Dachau were also used for forced labor.
They were employed to operate the field, in various projects of
construction and in small craft industries established in the countryside. They built roads,
They worked in quarries and drained swamps, all in terrible conditions.
During the war, the forced labor of concentration camp prisoners
became increasingly important for German arms production.
In the summer and autumn of 1944, to increase military production,
Satellite camps were established throughout southern Germany. These centers were under the
Dachau administration. Here alone, there were about 140 subcamps, where prisoners worked
almost exclusively in arms factories. Thousands of them worked themselves to death.
As the Allied forces advanced towards Germany, the Nazis began to move
to the prisoners of the concentration camps near the front to avoid, in this way,
the loss of their convicts. Evacuees from the eastern concentration camps arrived
continuously to Dachau, which caused a dramatic deterioration in the conditions of
the prisoners. With more than 30,000 prisoners, the camp was extremely overcrowded.
The barracks, built to hold 200 prisoners, were overcrowded with more than 1,600.
After days of travel, with barely anything to eat or drink, the prisoners arrived weak and exhausted, often at
on the brink of death. Due to overcrowding, poor sanitary conditions, and inadequate supplies
Insufficient and the prisoners' weak state, a typhus epidemic swept through Dachau,
killing between 100 and 200 prisoners a day. Of the 41,500 people who lost their lives
Between 1933 and 1945, more than a third died during the last six months of the war.
At the end of April 1945, the SS also began to evacuate the
prisoners of the Dachau concentration camp to prevent their release by the
Allied troops. At least 25,000 prisoners were sent to Tyrol on grueling journeys on foot.
During the so-called death marches, the Nazis shot anyone who
that could no longer continue. Many also died of hunger, hypothermia, or exhaustion.
Several thousand prisoners died during the evacuations.
On April 29, 1945, the main camp at Dachau was liberated by
units of the 45th Infantry Division. Before the American soldiers
arrived at Dachau, the camp commandant, Martin Weiss, had already fled. However,
There were still SS guards in the camp, who did not hesitate to shoot at the
American liberators. However, they soon surrendered to American superiority.
After the surrender of the guards, the American troops finally
were able to access the concentration camp facilities. However,
None of their previous combat experiences prepared them for what
was waiting for them. The first clue that something was terribly wrong was the smell.
As they approached the camp, American soldiers found more than 30
railway cars filled with corpses and in a state of decomposition. At that moment
They understood the source of the smell. It was the unbearable stench of death.
Inside the camp they found even more lifeless bodies, often naked,
lying everywhere. Sometimes the corpses were piled on top of each other like firewood.
For many soldiers, seeing these atrocities gave new meaning to war.
They realized that they were not just fighting an enemy, but pure evil.
The Nazis tried to incinerate all the bodies they could.
before leaving Dachau, but there were too many.
A soldier later recalled: "Wherever you look,
you feel the most complete horror. People are so close to death or
in a state of complete decrepitude, that you can't even process it."
As many of the American soldiers broke down in tears,
Others were filled with rage, anger and hatred.
When four German officers came out of the woods with a white handkerchief in their hands,
An American lieutenant ushered them into a packed wagon.
of corpses. He shot them right there. When the Germans, mortally wounded,
They screamed in agony, another American officer finished the job.
Later, the situation only got worse.
After American soldiers ordered SS guards to form up
A line along the wall of the coal yard, Lieutenant Walsh shouted "Let them
"Den!" and the American soldiers opened fire with rifles, pistols and machine guns
30-caliber. After a 30-second burst of gunfire, the Nazi guards were killed instantly.
However, even this was not the end.
The prisoners themselves, many of them tortured and treated worse than animals
During all these years, they also took revenge. While all the inmates
had lost at least one relative, some of them even had to
see their wives abused and raped. Others had to witness
Shooting competitions in which SS members threw small children into the air
while others shot them. Some saw their friends and family starve to death.
or during the death marches that took place shortly before the liberation.
Some inmates swore by all that was holy that if they ever had the chance to
kill their SS guards, they wouldn't hesitate. And they kept their word. When the prisoners caught
to the SS guards, they tried to escape. However, the prisoners caught them
They arrested them again and, this time, they killed them all, thus completing their revenge.
Other SS men and kapos were beaten to death by prisoners
with sticks, tools, or even their own fists. An American soldier was
witnessed an inmate stamping on an SS soldier's face until,
As he later stated, there was nothing left.
There were some SS guards who had changed their uniforms for clothes
from the concentration camp. However, they were recognized and lynched on the spot.
While all this was going on, both the prisoners and the American soldiers often
They stood motionless, watching coldly and mercilessly as revenge was carried out.
An American officer later said: "We stood by and watched them beat to death.
These guards. They beat them so much that, in the end, the bodies of these Nazis ended up
tearing and their guts spilling out. We watched these scenes with less
feeling than if they hit a dog." In fact, you could say that we were lacking
full of feelings. Deep anger and hatred had destroyed all our emotions."
Finding a kennel full of German Shepherds and Doberman Pinschers,
The American soldiers decided to also finish off these animals, since there were rumors circulating that
that the Nazis had fed the bodies of political prisoners to their dogs.
Later, American troops forced German citizens
from the city of Dachau to go to the camp to see for themselves,
the atrocities that were committed there and to help bury the bodies. Many of the
Local residents were shocked by such an experience and stated that they did not
They were aware of the barbarities that had been committed there for years.
To this day it is not clear how many guards of the
SS died, but the number is estimated to be between 30 and 50.
Because General Patton, then military governor of Bavaria,
dismissed all charges, no one has ever been brought to trial for this retaliation.
Of the more than 200,000 people who were imprisoned at Dachau and in
its numerous subsidiary fields during its 12 years of existence,
Between 1933 and 1945, almost 42,000 people were murdered.
Thanks for watching World History Channel don't forget to like and subscribe
and click on the notification bell so you don't miss out
our next videos thanks See you next time on the channel